<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truths triumpant; or, A familiar epistle from the Muffty of the Grand Cham of Tartary, to those fathers of falshood the Jesuites, whose superstitious doctrines are not only detected but derided, and reasons and natures eyes opened.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B06293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3172B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.4[224]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885046</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885046</idno>
            <idno type="VID">182893</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B06293)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 182893)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A4:2[225])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truths triumpant; or, A familiar epistle from the Muffty of the Grand Cham of Tartary, to those fathers of falshood the Jesuites, whose superstitious doctrines are not only detected but derided, and reasons and natures eyes opened.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Vast superstition! Glorious stile of weakness! ..."</note>
                  <note>On the same sheet, a letter explaining where the poem was found; signed: Philopatris. Philalethies.; text of letter begins: Right honourable, and noble patron of the religion, laws and libertys of all the free born people of England, ..".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-03</date>
            <label>Elspeth Healey</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:182893:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>And Noble Patron of the Religion, Laws and Libertys of all the Free Born People of <hi>England,</hi> who like a Star of the firſt Magnitude in <hi>Libra,</hi> outſhines all the Stars in our Hemisſphere, having <hi>Sol</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> for your Aſcendant, being not able to wait on your Lordſhip my ſelf, being forced by croſs Winds of Popiſh Faction and Malice to come to an Anchor in the <hi>Fleet;</hi> Upon pretence of not anſwering a Bill in <hi>Chancery</hi> put in or preferr'd by a Convict Papiſt and a Traytor, found ſo by the Grand Jury, but indeed an Atheiſt, that being but a pretence to hinder my appearance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King and Council; who have ſent for my Papers, and have them now as I am told in conſideration before them, but 'tis much to my prejudice, I ſuppoſe, I am not there, which I cannot be now without danger of my Perſon; having been, three times aſſaulted in the Street; and warning given me, by ſeveral perſons of Credit and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to have a care of my ſelf; Which Danger I ſuppoſe will encreaſe as Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries come on; ſo that God, I believe, in his kind Providence to his Glory and my good, I hope; has been pleaſed to hide me in the hollow of his hand, to be a means to Diſcover die hollowneſs of more Hearts than have yet been founded, and ſo to preſerve me till theſe Storms of State are overpaſt, turning that into a ſafe Harbor which they meant for a Quick-ſand to devour me; were I now but as well Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alled, as I am here ſecured from Winds, I ſhould not fear to ride it out till next Seſſions: if no Parliament ſits, I hope we ſhall not want a place to Try Whores and Knaves in, or we may ſhut up our Shops and make it a St. <hi>Innocents</hi> day.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I the rather make this Addreſs to your good Lordſhip, as having lately found in an old Magazine of a great Enemy of the Jeſuits, a Preſent, I hope, worth your acceptance in theſe Polemical times of Diſputation with thoſe Fathers of Falſhood, and Step-fathers of Truth the Jeſuits, being a Quiver of Arrows made by ſome <hi>Tartarian</hi> Prieſts of excellent piercing Points, where in a ſhort Familiar Epiſtle to them, they make the Vanity of their Superſtitious practices appear to be not only againſt Grace but Nature too, I thought my ſelf therefore as a true Son of the Proteſtant Church to enter my Proteſt againſt them; and give what Aid I could to their Deſtruction having ſought and ſtill do ſeek mine with ſo much Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Cruelty:nor knew I where to put theſe Arms in better hands in than theirs, that have uſed thoſe they have already managed with ſo much Generoſity, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Conſtancy, that your Honour may as well be called the <hi>Fabeus</hi> as Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Waller</hi> the <hi>Marcellus</hi> of this our Church and State; for if Religion ſtaggers, I find Law muſt reel; or, if you pleaſe rather to take the reſemblance of thoſe two Noble Active <hi>Romans,</hi> I mean <hi>Horatius Cocles</hi> and <hi>Mutius Scvola;</hi> the one defending our Bridge againſt the <hi>French Pourſenna,</hi> when they endeavoured to make one over our Noſes to our Deſtruction, the other boldly putting his hand into the Flame of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Malice to pull the Church of <hi>England</hi> like a brand out of the Fire of their Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, That I now begg of your Lordſhip, and of all true lovers of their Country is to lend me their aſſiſtance to ſubſiſt here without ſtarving, which has been and is til their Deſign, but I hope being here in this Fortreſs; ſecured from want of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition to gaul them more than if I were abroad, meaning from hence to play my great Guns to batter their <hi>Babylon,</hi> and deſtroy all their ſtrong Holds of Sin and Satan; Pray my Lord be pleaſed to accept this Sacrifice to you and my Country, having now put thoſe Arms into your hand of ſuch excellent truſty Steel with which you may eaſily Wound the Head of the Beaſt, and Heart of the Whore, overthrowing her Golden cup full of Superſtitious Liquor to the Ground, with Which ſhe hath made the Kings of the Nations drunk.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Philopatris. Philalethies.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_letter">
            <head>TRUTHS TRIUMPANT; Or, <hi>A Familiar Epiſtle from the</hi> Muffty <hi>of the Grand</hi> Cham <hi>of</hi> Tartary, <hi>to thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of falſhood the</hi> Jeſuites, <hi>whoſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Doctrines are not only detected but derided, and Reaſons and Natures Eyes opened.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>VAST <hi>Superſtition!</hi> Glorious ſtile of Weakneſs!</l>
               <l>Sprung from the deep diſquiet of Mans paſſion,</l>
               <l>To deſolation and deſpair of Nature.</l>
               <l>Thy Texts brings Princes Titles into queſtion:</l>
               <l>Thy Prophets ſet on work the ſword of Tyrants:</l>
               <l>They manacle ſweet Truth with their diſtinctions:</l>
               <l>Let Vertue blood: teach Cruelty for Gods ſake;</l>
               <l>Faſhioning one God, yet him of many faſhons,</l>
               <l>Like many-headed Errors, in their Paſſions.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mankind! Truſt not theſe <hi>Superſtitious</hi> dreams,</l>
               <l>Fears Idols, Pleaſures Relikes, Sorrows, Pleaſures:</l>
               <l>They make the willful hearts their holy Temples:</l>
               <l>The Rebels unto Government their Martyrs,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No: Thou child of falſe miracles begotten!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Falſe Miracles, which are but ignorance of Cauſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lift up the hopes of thy abjected Prophets:</l>
               <l>Courage, and Worth abjure thy painted heavens</l>
               <l>Sickneſs, thy bleſſings are; Miſery, thy tryal;</l>
               <l>Nothing, thy way unto eternal being;</l>
               <l>Death, to Salvation; and the Grave to Heaven</l>
               <l>So Bleſt be they, ſo Angel'd, ſo Eterniz'd</l>
               <l>That tye their ſenſes to thy ſenſeleſs glories,</l>
               <l>And dye, to cloy the after-age with ſtories.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Man ſhould make much of <hi>Life,</hi> as <hi>Natures table,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wherein ſhe writes the Cypher of her glory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Forſake not Nature, nor miſunderſtand her:</l>
               <l>Her miſteries are read without Faiths Eye-ſight</l>
               <l>She ſpeaketh in our Fleſh, and from our Senſes,</l>
               <l>Delivers down her wiſdoms to our Reaſon.</l>
               <l>If any man would break her laws to kill,</l>
               <l>Nature doth, for defence, alow offences.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>She neither taught the Father to deſtroy:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor promis'd any man, by dying, joy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For, were not mankind by themſelves oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Kings would not, Tyrants could not, make them Beaſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
